good morning this thing of getting up
earlier doesn't work either here anyway
I tried okay let's start with the
meditation okay
let me tell you about the meditation
first okay
before you close your eyes or you can
close your eyes and sleeping just get it
psychically I think at meditation number
18 page eight okay
we're going to start the meditations and
the long room book are starting going to
start to touch on the refuge vows so
these twelve vows and this is the kind
of the first one that directly addresses
that and it does mean once you take
refuge in the Buddha jewel let me read
you the vowel don't seek refuge in
worldly objects and deities after you
have taken refuge in the Buddha so
anybody here who has a Buddhist name
you took this back okay already and it's
nice to understand about dig more deeply
so I I spent a lot of time thinking
about this Val and I in my feeling in
the modern world there are different
religions you know there are Buddhism
Christians Jews Hindus Muslims you know
there are lots of different religions
and they have different teachings my
Christian says that God took six days to
make the world and then on the seventh
day took a rest and that's why we should
go to church and Sunday something like
that the old religion of Tibet burn
assess that the world was created by a
monkey who God had sex with over a witch
or something like that okay something
like that and every religion has a
different idea where the world came from
who's running the world okay but it
seems to me in my how I see things how I
see the world and I travel a lot so I
get to see many countries and I see them
once a year twice a year it's like I see
there's almost no place where we don't
go you know we just got invited to
Africa and I think we'll go because it's
South South Africa so I kind of see what
people believe in and what they all
believe in is science is cell phone and
to be honest you know I think the
religion or the belief of this world is
it cell phones you know and it's shared
by all in all we call it religion I mean
like Muslim people believe in cell
phones Christian people believe in cell
phones Jewish people believe in stuff
songs and you know if your cell phone
breaks and you you give the personal
choice you can you can pray to Muhammad
or you can pray to Yahweh or you could
pray to God or you can take it to the
cell phone fixing store they will choose
the cell phone fixing store they don't
go to the church or the synagogue and
pray that the cell phone will work you
see and they don't try to fix someone
else's stuff oh okay
I've taught seeds - I had a children's
group for many years it was my fourth
power for the for the mistake I made
with an abortion so for 15 years I
taught a children's group and one day in
New York we were I don't know if you
remember it was at Leon's place and I
was teaching this kids group in the air
conditioner broke and it was really hot
New York red New York hot summer day and
and me and this other teacher we got up
on a ladder and we were trying to fix
the air conditioner and the kids were
running around and going crazy and and
then this little boy came and grabbed my
pant legs and he pulled it you know he
said no no gusli Michael you know and
don't do that I'm like just be quiet I'm
trying to fix it no no you're not please
me
I think I'm just you know go play I'm
trying to teach him she said you should
go outside find another person who air
conditioned is broken and how can fix it
that's the winner
[Laughter]
[Music]
so everybody believes in engines and
motors and the internet and computers
and that's the real religion of the
world we have our culture our parents
you know get lit a menorah on what
Friday nights or our parents through
painting each other on Diwali or dressed
up on let's at home
please yeah I was in Tel Aviv in Yassa
I'm for him which is a religious
Halloween and everybody was dressed up
as a angels and I was so happy you know
and I had to give a talk at the yappa
theatre things 800 people and I got out
of that car
in my robes and some guy runs up to me
says hey cool mother for you even though
just like them that's a nice costume
so we have our religious culture
Christmas dinner or you know Christmas G
Christmas songs but but what people
really believe in is science everybody
you know believes deeply and a big part
of their life is their cell phone what's
this called you ready
they left their cellphone in the taxicab
and then people go crazy people go like
it's like they someone just told them
they have cancer you know so people
don't even so for me what we have to
compete with is not other religions like
I don't think this valve first of all
first refuge valve I encourage you don't
see oh I'm not Hindu we don't like
Hindus I'm not Muslim we don't like
Muslims you know don't don't think like
that okay what we don't like is selfless
okay what we're competing with is cell
phones okay people believe the cell
phone works because wrong Shia and her
friends but pieces in this thing she's a
manager for Apple in in Shanghai you
know with the move that the cell phone
works because these people in Fox come
they put the pieces in the plastic and
that's why it works and we remove that
and and that's the religion we are
competing with okay that's the one which
is wrong okay why does cell phone work
what would the boy say in my kids class
[Music]
you have someone else communicate you
see you have two other people
communicate then your cell phone will
never break
you got it okay what's the Karma for the
cover breaking I don't know
we have to figure it out not being clear
to people okay so this meditation at
number 18 its to try to recognize inside
of you you your real religion is suffer
you know or car or airplane you know and
you believe that okay you believe the
way to get from Singapore to LA San
Francisco San Francisco is to get on a
plane you believe doesn't and you
believe that the plane works if it has
all the metal parts you believe that you
know you don't understand that how you
got some Singapore to San Francisco was
that you helped other people get to
where they want to go otherwise the
flight would be canceled or they would
pull you off the plane if it was United
something like that
and it's very hard because we're
surrounded by seven billion people who
believe in science and you have to
struggle with it so in this meditation
you can think about anything how you're
going to call your family when you when
you get home how you're going to get
home on an airplane or in a car and you
have to think about what makes the
airplane work and what makes the car
work or what makes the cell phone work
okay and if you can't overcome your
belief in the religion of science then
then you will never reach enlightenment
it's not possible okay I don't mean you
should hate your cell phone you should
love your cell phone you know I love my
cell phone and I use it for good things
and bad things too but you know they're
very valuable they're very precious they
are unbelievably cool but understand
where it comes from
okay and that's taking refuge when you
understand what really makes a cell
phone work when you think about it you
are taking refugees and then that taking
refuge helps to destroy your old bad
seeds it creates new good seeds your
life becomes magical everything we try
is successful okay you love other people
okay so this meditation is the most
important one he said that about four
other ones say okay now we're ready to
mention I can't ready here we go
number 18 maybe you want to do this one
everyday one time
so relax your forehead put a little
smile on your face hold in your stomach
just a little bit tight relax your
fingers relax your eyelids check your
shoulders are they relaxed and then
let's come to our breath
long exhales let's not count to be let's
just watch exhales long exhales and
bring the mind to the center with the
breath
then we'll start a meditation please
look into your heart and connect with
your heart teacher do you know like kind
of sneak into the grain of children and
submit bills
and to be with them no special clamour
agenda just be quiet with them enjoy
being with your heart teacher
then during their three-day retreat we
won't use our cell phone and then when
we come out of retreat I think it's
thirsty or Freddie we will most of us
will grab our cell phone and text
somebody reach out somebody I'd like you
to think of two or three people that you
will probably contact with your cell
phones or your laptop after you get out
of the three-day retreat all of us have
some busy things we have to do we have
plans after this program but also after
this few days we we feel that we will
need to write someone text someone we
chat so try to think of two or three
people that you might be sending us
reach out to as soon as you take down
your boundary marker or as soon as you
reach the temple okay here we go
and
in China China imagine that someone
comes up to you and says oh that's a
nice cellphone and I heard about huawei
cell phones and how does it work and
then you know we're not scientists and
we have a teacher in our life that we
talk into the phone and we push a button
and then a circuit closes and
electricity goes across some wires and
some of us remember from seventh grade
science class electrons are moving to a
pipe or something and then somehow it
comes out of the phone as a signal and
it goes and touches tower cell phone
tower and then there's more electrons
moving in the cell phone tower along
copper wires and then another signal
goes out and go to a satellite and
there's more wires in the stands iron
more electrons move and then signals
come from the satellite to my friend in
Singapore to my husband
my children and that's how we explain a
cellphone if you and me had to make a
cell phone it would take a thousand
years I think but we have a rough idea
how it works so get in touch with that
rough picture in your mind mostly from
7th grade science class about how the
cell phone is working because somebody
asked your question about it after you
finished your three-day retreat
how does your cell phone work
[Music]
and then try to take refuge which means
which always means look at the deeper
causes what makes the copper carry
electrons who made satellites go up into
space who built that cell phone tower
why am i able to communicate with people
I love and do things I think are
important with this cell phone and then
try to think about the real causes then
I don't know the clearly all the causes
but I I believe it must have to do with
helping other people to communicate
maybe a husband or wife that you know
they have trouble communicating with
each other and maybe you help them or
maybe you taught a child to read or you
explained your understanding of Dharma
to other people you shared so try to
figure out yourself
what has caused the cellphone what keeps
them working
now if you weren't meditating I would
ask you if you want to go deeper but
since you can't talk I I believe you
want to go deeper so you can take this
meditation to a deeper level and think
about messages you're getting nowadays
who's been writing you who's been
posting things that you read what family
members or friends are using which I've
to contact you and think about some of
the messages you've gotten I try not to
read them before I go to bed because
some of them disturb my mind good ones
and bad ones mmm think about messages
you get on your cell phone and try to
understand that they are also coming
from you good ones that you're getting
nowadays bad ones what you see on the
internet this week news entertainment
all the content of your cell phone not
just a cell phone is also coming from
you and from your sins
and all this kind of thinking all this
kind of meditation is taking refuge
because it will protect you you can keep
yourself on working if you help others
to communicate then you can only get
beautiful messages and see inspiring
uplifting things on the internet if you
speak that way to other than you
communicate that weight on it and that's
taking refuge
thank your number and you're right
that's probably one of the main jobs of
anomalies to keep you thinking like this
and then come back here breath sweet nan
exhale and then slowly open your eyes
take a
you okay any questions I don't think so
okay up Thank You geshe-la
can you also protect your communication
by buying a case for your cell phone my
my best friend bought a case for their
cell phone then they dropped it and it
broke so yes you can buy a kit you still
have to do all the normal stuff you know
is blasted by a case whether it works or
not will depend on whether you have
respected other people's property you
see so I'm not trying to say don't use
cell phones anymore I'm not trying to
say don't put cases on your cell phone
I'm not trying to say don't go to we're
building an emergency mini cell phone
tower for people who get bit by snakes
and stuff you still have to do those
things but they won't work unless you
help other people that's all but but
don't stop taking aspirin don't stop you
know
don't throw yourself on out your family
won't be happy okay we talked about
deeper causes not not not that there's
no apparent causes okay no condition are
your questions are too hard so when we
receive the message before person type
the message they have a thinking process
about this message and they heard this
because that when is the seed before two
years yes good good good on my
responsible for their planting seeds to
hear that first offenders message so I
can yeah that's a good question
sorry Pete when Anton said let's say I
get a not very nice message on my phone
we tell from somebody and that's
attacked by another person on their
phone or they spoke into the phone and
then there's a call that Lily chicken
nothing additive identity gain assembled
on tha second line of the epidemic
Roshan fourth chapter anytime you do
anything anytime you say anything a
thought comes just before which is raw
karma and so what Anton said is is
somebody that person who sent you maybe
a not very positive message they had a
thought that came just before to say
something to you which is not nice or
something like that so
Anton's question is and in Anton said I
understand that thought to type a
negative message came out of a seed
karmic scene in their mind and then he
asked did I plant that seed and if that
might fall if that my responsibility you
know did I put a bad city in the other
person's of mine you see sandy daiva has
a controversial part about that he said
if that person who says a bad thing to
you because you made a karma right and
they go to hell because you made a karma
then you said them to health
[Music]
but by saying something bad to somebody
last week okay
I personally don't believe it you know I
can't plant us meaning I I believe that
if the other person had a good come they
would believe they're trying to help me
they're sending me this kind of hard
message tough message to help me their
motivation is to help me so I believe
that how they feel about what they sent
me how that affects them is coming from
their karma not from mine but from my
sense that the seed was planted by my
bad karma you seen I mean so you can
take the karmic scene in their mind
which opened into the idea to send me a
message and you can split it okay
they're going to experience something
good from sending me a kind they feel
it's a kind suggestion then the other
half I I'm going to interpret the same
thing as something negative you okay got
it so one seed can be good karma and bad
come at the same time
okay got it some mice it's like a pen
something to chew or something to write
okay so but can I hurt them by forcing
them to send me a bad message no I don't
believe it
Chandi Davis says that but I think it's
just to make us try to be better people
I don't think it's correct okay
and I don't think he thinks it's correct
okay nice question other Russian
let's give more and let's do more in the
afternoon okay more questions in the
action okay
nineteen meditation number 19 we have 27
I'm afraid we won't finish that's what I
usually do this what's the second refuge
commitment by the way the first refuge
commandments are negative don't do this
yeah once you've taken refuge in Dharma
you can't hurt anything or anybody
anymore okay that's the second refuge
commitment if if you are in Thailand you
you heard them recently if you weren't I
mean jing-mei and Phil teach them every
time I guess right so second refuge
commitment don't hurt other people in
the long run book when we get to there
it's going to say what's a sign that a
person is taking refuge successfully
okay how do you know someone is a
successful refuge taker okay and what's
the answer they're nice to everybody
okay like when you say Tonto secret
Buddhism
you know highest Buddhism what comes in
people's minds I don't know I think a
lot of people see some people see people
killing chickens and spraying blood on
people and some people say see people
having sex and some people see a llama
in a big heart I'm going to go
you know but what it really is is
something like I don't know Takia or
Roberson girl or Adam they're just nice
people you think that's a high hard
tantric person they are nice to
everybody okay
if not they have a special dollar okay
special heart that's how you can tell oh
this person must be practicing hybridity
this is a high Buddhist practitioner
because they're just nice to everybody
okay
just sweet to everybody more and more
sweet okay
so we're not going to do the meditation
this morning but 19 when you get to 19
you can think about am i successful in
my refuge practice and that's why refuge
is the basis of countries okay am I
being nice to other people okay if you
take refuge then it means you understand
that things are coming from you if you
understand that things are coming from
you you will always be nice okay so the
same that a person understands refuge is
that they never hurt anybody okay
they don't say things that hurt other
people they don't do things that are
dangerous like talking on your cell
phone when you're driving you know
they're just super careful not to hurt
other people you know somebody was
telling me
Howard Connie react to this dinner we
had a really bad dinner the other day
and
and some of the things now I just think
of it like Connie would you think of it
you know like how would you talk to this
person and we had a really having a fun
time you're saying
Connie would say you really put this on
the plate nice a lot of different
ingredients anyway that's a saying that
your message so they've not decided
someone took refuge okay and that's a
sign of tantric practice okay they're
just nice to people so he's talking
about the result of refuge right what
you said if you it's that slow time if
you understand emptiness you understand
that nothing happens without you you'd
behave in some way towards other people
if you understand that which is
dependent origination you take refuge
meaning you don't do things that are
going to hurt you later
and that's protection and then you're a
nice person so if a person is nice who
went to many DCI programs or something
we hope it's because they understood
sees direct and that's a sign that they
have refuge okay so obviously it's
difficult to judge if other people
what they're thinking right but we can
judge what we're thinking and we can
decide about ourselves you know in my a
successful refuge sticker okay so that's
meditation number 19 number 20
okay number 20 I put I took me a long
time I found a photo of somebody putting
water in a good cup of coffee and
ruining it okay I don't know if you've
ever had somebody do that you know like
they have enough coffee for three cups
and four people show up my mom used to
do this she had four boys and no husband
around and he got paid on Friday on
Saturday we had orange juice on Sunday
we had half orange juice and half water
on Monday I was one third or thirdly of
course - okay
and and there's a refuge tradition which
is don't watered-down your refuge okay
like don't mix other stuff into it you
know okay it's like you hear things from
people you know like I like this idea
that you can fix an air conditioner by
helping other people with their air
conditioner so burn it's the people who
say but after that okay but you know
that's nice idea but no no let's be
practical
you know some I understand that Sudama
point of view but tell me the practical
point of view you know and you got to
look at them and say the diamond point
is you know again people say be
practical don't go to love me more in
time I want to make money I want to have
a successful relationship I want to be
healthy you know it is this is the most
practical thing this is the thing that
works okay so don't let down water down
your refuge like 50% refuse 30% refuse
okay I trust if I help other people
I'll have a good a good business but you
know I kind of have to cheat people now
to get there now you don't know how many
people tell me I mean they don't say it
like that
but they mean that and when we get to
this section in book later it's a hard
section because he's very critical of
things that don't work you know and he
chooses some other world years that were
in his country in his life in his time
like there was a there was a world deal
called birth people called bon bon Paul
but it's called burn okay and they
believed that the world was created by
this person and they had a data belief
they still exist and some people told
this Lama you know my parents were
burned they believed the world was made
by Chambourcin
and so I kind of like to be 50/50 is
that okay like I'll all six other
people's air conditioners but also make
a paradise chamber you know is that okay
you know and he says well if you keep
doing that it's like orange juice you
know it's just not going to be very
strong the refuge won't be very strong
okay so it's up to you I don't mean
disrespect your parents I don't mean
that I go to church I went to church a
couple weeks ago and it makes my family
happy and and I learned good things I
learned some good things you know and
that's okay but keep your keep your
world you protect your worldview don't
water it down don't put water and good
food Starbucks cup of coffee okay
everything's coming from me 100% don't
be a fifty percent comes from me fifty
percent comes from something else
okay I mean keep that deal I have a
close Christian sense they said can i
still can I still pray to God I said
yeah I'm no problem it's coming from you
you know that's okay
how can a person come from me and take
care of me you made your mother you made
your father you know it's possible it's
okay in Buddhism we say
Biagio Guinea made the world okay though
I made by jogini okay that's okay
okay but but below it is this belief
that everything comes from you and how
you treat other people
and I don't think it's contradicts most
of the great religions if you study the
30 pages of the New Testament Jesus's
words we didn't like pull out this whole
conversation about planting seeds on
rocky soil or good soil and he's talking
about seeds all the time you know and
that's the main thing and Mohammed was
the same so no problem mayo and tea okay
but don't put water in your okay because
it won't help you okay everything comes
from you everything comes from how you
treat other people everything is your
fault okay okay all right
so I guess during that meditation you
might think about you know are you
watering down your understanding about
seeds you know do you how much do you
believe a cell phone comes from you you
know 30% 25% try to raise the percent
try to struggle your whole life to raise
the percent and it always comes from me
and yours another part of the sentence
from how I treated other people okay
it's always comes from me from how I
treated other people and the building
blocks of of existence are not atoms
they are kindnesses okay you got to get
there you got to get to where you you
feel that in your heart you know this
computer is not made of iron atoms and
silicon atoms and copper atoms those
atoms are made of kindness
okay it has copper atoms it has steel
atoms it has aluminum atoms but those
atoms are held together by kindness how
I treat other people okay you gotta
reach that place sooner or later in your
life okay question we'll see when we get
there I think it does yeah I think it
does yeah there's a there's a refuge Val
number three which is after you take
refuge in Sangha we are encouraged not
to associate too closely with people who
think this is all crazy okay not does
that mean you can't have a Christian
friend or Muslim planner it doesn't mean
that
what's the sign of good refuge yeah
you're just nice to everybody okay you
don't say oh you you don't believe
copper atoms were made by how you
treated your your your wife's last week
I don't like you you know you know and
you know I pray that this organization
never becomes like that and I don't know
how you know we have to be really
careful you know I taught 18 stamps in
the teacher training of how to teach the
pen second-by-second how to teach the
pen it took an hour or two hours 18
different things you have to do in a
two-minute presentation of the pen you
know and then a week later somebody came
up to me and said I think it's 17
you know and then suddenly in my mind
came this future thing they'll be the
seventeen steps and religion and they'll
be the 18 step ten religion and they
will hate each other and they will have
war you know and you know we have to be
careful that it doesn't become like that
okay so this vow it's dangerous if I was
dangerous
okay it means it means you know this
one's really hard I mean you have to try
to protect your view of the world from
the whole world okay the whole world
believes copper atoms the whole world
every religion person in the world has
the same religion called science copper
atoms copper atom copper atom ISM once
everyone is there copper atom is in the
whole world and again then you know try
to spend when you choose your close
friends try to choose friends like I
said Katie's mom Janice when I was
talking about ten ways to fundraise
she's just looking at me like I'm crazy
and I've got really uncomfortable you
know I said are you okay yeah I'm okay
so what are you thinking and she said
well isn't helping other people with
their fundraising the way to fundraise
no my you know and you want that kind of
people around you you see that's all you
want to stay close to that kind of
people who can't correct you get you
Michael when you have some other idea
you see I mean okay that's all all right
let's do 21 meditation 21 we're going to
finish I'm sure
Oh 9:30 I'll give you a break six more
minutes okay all right I keep
remembering this advice from the most
popular teacher at Princeton they
interviewed him and he said the main
thing is let students out early they
will love you even if it's two minutes
three minutes I'm just telling you guys
teacher trick good teacher training
I'm not your students out early are you
HOT anyone how many people warm raising
him how many people not don't want to
air conditioning you're a surgeon okay
you win
recently I was out with the day I went
to church and I promised myself a good
breakfast out you know at a restaurant
if I went to church because you have to
get up you have to get up early this is
how my mom used to bribe me to go to
church and so I went to church and then
it ended early and there is no good
restaurant wearing there on Sunday
nothing you know I even went to the
casino and I said you guys have Sundberg
to like no I like alright then that that
filled out the place l-fatiha that we
got we have a little Mexican restaurant
close to us it's good food but it
doesn't open till noon so I had like
half an hour in my car I have to wait to
help out of my car so there's this
Native American monument near my house
it's called Montezuma castle it's on the
side of a cliff
it's huge it's very big and it was made
a thousand years ago 1,400 years ago and
they made it and they used to live there
and then suddenly they disappeared
nobody knows why they made many houses
like this around my house there are
there are about a thousand places
smaller than this nobody knows what
happened to them I think their air
conditioners broke they went someplace
else anyway when I was a kid you used to
climb up there and now they don't like
they don't allow it no okay but I had
half an hour I never been there I lived
there for seven years it's it's five
minutes from my house I never went there
so I said I'm gonna go look at it you
know and it's interesting because the
people are gone right who lived there
but the place is there and and the place
proves that there used to be people
there that's all so I took a picture
this place I put it okay
the place proves that the people were
there okay and and in the refuge
tradition we are encouraged to be honest
that we never met Buddha okay are you
Buddhist yes who's Buddha lived 2,000
years ago are you sure I think so but
you're a Buddhist you don't know if they
lived or not yeah well I don't know my
mom said so like that you see like there
becomes a question in British and in
Christian too must
you know are you sure this person lived
you never did you meet them no do you
follow them yes I can then in Buddhism
we say I have gym canteen I have seen
Dean had these beautiful teachings about
seeds four steps for powers four by four
five by four you know there is a flag my
father this is secret
you know and I have those teachings and
and to me they prove a person who was
not like anybody else in the world you
know who wasn't a copper animist okay
there was a person who came to this
world and said no it doesn't work that
way it works it differently you know the
whole world didn't believe it they
caught copper atom mist okay and then
one person came and said no that's
that's wrong that's not how anything
works it's because it's not just wrong
it's completely wrong okay
somebody told me the first link in The
Wheel of Life is a lack of an
understanding no no no no no no no it's
a misunderstanding okay it's not a lack
of understanding so basa bandha will hit
you on the head two times if you say
that do that dharma sangha no I think
God is going to do
now here are the help no no no the first
leg is not a lack of understanding its
misunderstanding okay
cotton copper atom is misunderstand
where the world comes from it's not that
they don't understand its opposite they
believe the opposite they believe you
can ignore a friend who's having trouble
with their husband or their wife and
your cellphone was to work they believe
that right guy that misunderstanding
it's not lack of understand got it so
one person came into this world your
world that you were born into okay and
one person came and said no that's not
the way it works one person against a
billion you know and and we're lucky
because people started to believe it and
they wrote down what he said and we have
those books and we have a tradition we
have a lineage okay
and this lineage I you're an idiot right
you're the next lineage Lama okay you
are I don't know forty three or
something like that
you are the nice one something like I
don't confuse me and I can count them
for you if you want but you are the next
one okay and you have to keep it pure
you have to keep it pure okay two and a
half thousand years people didn't mess
up this explanation and if you mess it
up
you first person in two and a half
thousand years okay yeah things coming
from you but you know not everything you
know then you just destroyed two and a
half thousand years BC so you have a big
responsibility in the monastery they say
you're not allowed to go to a teaching
unless you can take responsibility to
teach it again yourself
so Chinese people take notes Americans
don't I don't know I guess Americans
have better memory or maybe they have
the knowledge base but uh you know it's
your responsibility to to pass it on
so how do we know there existed Buddha
jewel from the evidence we have okay
from the buildings they left okay we can
believe it so when you do that
meditation you can ask yourself you know
why do I believe in this person who I
can't see I can't talk to them there's
no video there's a joke in Europe they
say Americans only believe something is
it in a movie things that don't slanted
told me that so you know we don't have
video we don't have photos but we have
the teachings okay so we can believe
that there existed this person okay now
on the day you see emptiness directly
you will see the Buddha directly you
will need them directly okay
on that day you confirm with director
section what you deduced from the
evidence before okay different
experience then you can confirm there's
Buddha okay until then you are using
deduction but on the day you see empty
mr. Dai resting you will meet the Buddha
the Buddha didn't die Buddha still there
you can lose them directly and you will
never be the same after that
okay you will never be the same after
that by the way good news
which relates to your debate today is
that you also see your future Buddha
self yourself on the same day you see
ahead and we can see yourself become a
Buddha already okay and teaching and
doing all this nice things okay so on
that day you can see yourself as a you
can see what you're going to look like
what you're going to talk about okay you
can see that okay it's cool 500 years
ahead okay you want to go deeper or you
want to go to the bathroom
let's go do this for one minute and as
you're going to learn in debate class
today and the debate class of you taught
by Nick and Adam and my idea is Katie
and Aaron also okay because women are
better arguer than men are you know that
I mean all the men know that I know but
there's an important form of taking
refuge which is called result refuge
okay it's called result refuge you're
going to learn five kinds of refuge in
debate class today okay you can learn
five different kinds one the coolest one
the fifth one is called result refuge
and it means you can do prayers to a
future Buddha named my
Milica Daniel and turn okay Anton can
take refuge in a future butakov Anton
they will call your hand by the way that
does you have a nice name okay okay got
it that the fifth kind of refuge the
coolest one is that aggression see in
the future Buddha called you and I did
that I told you sometimes I was having a
hard day in my dining business like very
busy and the boss is yelling I mean you
know calling me stupid and probably I
did do something stupid you know and I
feel tired I feel sad and nervous too
much pressure then I would meditate but
I can't meditate in my office because I
built my office on a glass on purpose I
built it in the middle of the floor
I built it everybody can see what I'm
doing I'm the boss
everybody can see everything I'm doing
and it helps the whole company because
they know I'm not just relaxing they can
see I'm doing something so I built the
office on a block and so I don't have
any privacy so I used to go to their
toilet and close it I do it number two
okay
in a boy's bathroom it's more private
and I go in there I sit down I don't
open the toilet I just sit on the top
then I'll say you know to my future
Buddha because teacher Buddha can see
all the pastimes see souther hey my
future Buddha Mike I'm having a hard day
you know and I got mad at my boss
I'm sorry I delayed you because I got a
I apologize it's probably take
another thousand years
for you to become Buddha and I just want
you to know I'm sorry and I'm trying
really hard just having a hard day you
know so you can talk to your future
Buddha because they can hear you and
that's a special kind of refuge okay if
you're having a really hard day and you
don't have any friend to talk to you can
talk to your future bird because they
are watching you right now
you know man like come on hurry up okay
hurry up and go to the bathroom okay
we're going to do a meditation so please
get ready very good to sit the
cappuccino before me
check your cell phone get some Michael
relax your eyelids relax the corners of
your mouth
relax your hands pull them back a little
bit it straightens your back and your
chest comes out
and I'd like to do the breathing a
little bit different so your central
tell John John my comes to a place the
opening is between your eyebrows little
bit up from the eyebrows and this is
where the end of your central channel
comes out and sometimes when you do the
breathing meditation you can do it from
this place this hole so I'd like you to
watch your exhales long exhales but
please do it from the point between your
eyebrows groove armadas in Sanskrit
and so you're not breathing through your
nose actually the breath coming and
glide to your nose but imagine that is
coming in and out of this spot between
your eyebrows and up a few a few
millimeters and let's practice breathing
from very long exhales it will help you
to focus
and please come to your heart and make a
connection with the longer there you can
crawl into the grain of sugar like a
little tent and sit with your llama so
you are withdrawn and pratyahara from
the outer world you're deep inside your
heart and you're quiet inside a tiny
space with your teacher
and look at them make sure it's clear
the visualization as if they were really
there breathing warm fragrance
and I'd like you to think about a
Buddhist image that you are familiar
with maybe it's a painting maybe it's a
Buddha statue some kappa Torah Buddha
coin you're you just some image
photograph painting carving something
you're you see pretty often maybe it's
in your home on your alternate think
about this image try to get the details
of it in your mind what does the face
look like what did here's the play what
does the mouth look like is it sitting
with standing bring some image to mind
I'd like you to try to imagine where was
this image made I have heard some copper
statue I don't know exactly I think it
was made in Nepal I tried to imagine the
person who made it or painted it
or cracked it go back in time trace the
lineage of this image back to a workshop
or a studio and somebody with painting
carving
and they were using a model day they had
a different image maybe a photograph
[Music]
painting carving of an earlier version
of your image so try to go back in time
to the day your image was finished in
the studio or workshop or factories and
the person was looking at a model of an
earlier image in my case of some copper
now go back again to the day that second
image was finished and that maybe you
have to imagine the place where maybe it
was finished we don't know exactly in my
case this metal statue the third one I
think might have been carved and I'm
just guessing or imagining maybe it was
carved in in a workshop and some very
careful
Nepalese artisan was carving a similar
image to mine three generations ago
and they're using a model a fourth
dimension earlier image
and now skip back to the first one that
was ever made and somebody sought jetsam
copper or tolerable buddha in fact i
found in an ancient art book and they
said that first painted image of Buddha
was the Wheel of Life and that's the
great grandfather of all images of the
blueness and that was made by someone
who was looking at the Buddhist so with
your image whether it's Tara going in
gouda so copper let's go back to the
very first image and someone had the
good fortune someone had the good karma
to be sitting in front of the Buddha the
real Buddha or some cobbler and what
someone had the really good karma to sit
in front of her tantric daily angel like
Taro's corneas
all images of all holy beings in this
world started when someone was looking
at or thinking about the real one
trying to imagine that first sitting you
know so much lucky enough to see time
going in and they are trying to capture
that in a painting or a sculpture
now please come back to your image in
your home or your on your altar nor
you're wrong the first image we started
with in my case it's at some couple nice
statue someone gave me it's on the altar
in my bedroom come back to that image
first one that you were thinking about
and now try to feel different about this
image in it don't think Factory don't
think store think oh this is a
ultimately this image started with the
real person or their real tantric dare
your angel someone saw them this statue
I have is almost like proof this statue
that I have is is the footprint of some
cover
and it's very valuable and very rare and
I'm so lucky to have it
and then come back to the llama in front
of you thank them in your mind
for this pleasant meditation
then come back to your forehead to be
long breath from this place of focus
and you can slowly open your eyes take a
stretch so the goal of that meditation
is to help you keep your reference Val
just wanna thank you yeah yeah number
four
so the fourth refuge now is to respect
images of the Buddha
when I first study with my lover
one of my Jobs was to claim that temple
a lot yeah I got to know the temple very
well and I would he was a move that
imaging and cleaned the altar and then I
would grab the image by the head and my
momma would like hit me you know okay
you can't grab to a cobbler by the head
you know you have to pick him up by the
bottom you know you have to show some
respect you know okay so and I I'll tell
you honestly I mean it's another thing
that happens on the day you see
emptiness directly the meditation we
just did will have a direct experience
you think you you have a because you see
the Buddha directly then when you come
out when you get out your whole
relationship with images changes you
know so I'm not I'm not the kind of
person that keeps us very good altar I
have friends who have hundred images in
their house and miss dr. Wu if you ever
go to his house it's it's cool there's
no place for people it's all Buddhist
you know I I don't do that I just come
after you have a fear and and to be
honest I don't look at them very awesome
they just became part of my house you
know in but on the day you see emptiness
your relationship to paintings and
sculptures statues it changes you get
very I don't know you feel different
about them that they almost do in my
life okay and we become very they feel
very precious to you and you feel very
honored to have them okay and maybe they
will be a day in this world there will
be a day when people you know don't
remember what this image was or who it
is it's like the photographs of you you
know there will be a day when the last
one gets thrown away mister who is this
I don't know
grandfather's father some they just
throw it out and in the last picture of
you in this world will be thrown out by
summer including so much house you know
and they say well this is guys weird and
there will come a day in this world when
you can't get a broom you see and so
they're precious and and and one of the
parts of this vow is to be is to not
judge the quality of the painting and
not judge the quality of the statue you
know and there's a there's a joke it's
well there's a there's a tradition that
if you see a Buddha statue that's not
made very well you aren't allowed to say
after you take refuge in Buddha you're
not allowed to say that's an ugly statue
because you're talking about Lord Buddha
okay so it's supposed to say the artist
was not my skills so sometimes I go with
my friends can move live and don't think
I don't know there's not the artist was
not so strong
it moves so what somebody said that's a
lily again we had a really bad dinner -
missing the cook was not so skilled
that's a refuge solution so that the
goal of this meditation is to get a
bigger appreciation for the Buddha
images you have and maybe we want to get
some more and have them around maybe you
want to end up like mr. Rhyne and in the
monastery people give us they give the
monastery images and we have hundreds we
have too many to put in the temple so we
will rotate them and they they bought
lockers like athletic lockers and they
keep you know week number one locker one
does Buddhist good to be in the temple
and then week number two a locker to it
they get to do it and it's a lot of work
to change the images and now Diamond
Mountain starting to collect I got like
ten more for you people gave me like
priceless diamond cutter sutures and
stuff there's one that rolls out from
about here to the wall I don't have room
in my house so I'm going to give it to
you guys you have to remember okay and
we're playing some at college so we're
going to get a bigger appreciation and
that's part of taking refuge okay
because many many countries have
pictures of angels you know like this
one here I think it's mimicker Berlin do
you know moon skin' munchkin
this one's billing yeah or maybe a scam
I don't remember but Paris has beautiful
ones
Mexico City oh my gosh a whole smooth in
the middle of two streets they're going
into the downtown there's how many
twenty thirty angel statues one by one
on these huge pillars okay
and that's good we should be happy you
know all these churches have angels and
all these Muslim books have angel son we
should be happy it means somebody in
that country saw angel you see or met
someone who saw an angel you see so when
you see a statue of an angel in Mexico
or Germany or or flying in in China
you should be happy Oh somebody's sorry
okay
and you should be excited okay now maybe
I can and if you keep them around you
have a bigger chance of seeing them okay
all right let's do two more just talk
about them 23 is people offering food
okay and it's a big custom in my the
people who translated the food prayers
they asked me what this word grace okay
in English we say grace and grace has
three meanings okay one is the person
moves with grace like when they walk did
they almost look like they are dancing
okay that's called grace in English this
person is very graceful
okay the second meaning of grace is
blessing of the Lama or black
God God's grace and then the third
lenient grace means before you eat
before you drink you you offer to do the
first okay all right okay to the three
jewels you offering so this is a refuge
now what number is number eight okay
you should offer the first part of
anything you eat or drink okay and
what's the emergency prayer yeah like no
like this
okay like the last home it's also sick
but you know you should get in the habit
offering always okay and like all
religious things it becomes a bad habit
you know you're like oh you don't think
about it anymore that's a danger for all
of us you don't think about it such as
will give you salvation do that they are
walking
Doku known archaeological so China not
giving a bad you know take some take a
moment we're very very busy all of us
are busy
I'm Dharma busy me and it's gotten or we
read Dharma busy we're doing Dharma all
over the world all the time and
sometimes we all have
I think about it you know you know try
to pause and because we like to eat
three or four or five 10 times a day we
can get three or four five or ten
chances to pause and connect with our
recipes okay with the with the two
jewels
okay so learn to do this you can
practice in retreat cuz you're not busy
okay three days will come spending three
minutes
go to the end of the book take the pair
you like the grace okay it doesn't have
to be a Christian word okay can be a
brutish Marine British grace and it and
pick the one okay first one three jewels
by the way that yeah okay the Tibetans
also here if you want to learn it the
pronunciation is here but I always say
do it in your own language okay second
one is a grace for your teachers if
you're feeling like you want to make an
offering to your teacher of ding dong or
cupcake hostess cupcake husband whatever
bad food you're having okay so would
it's a great if you want to improve your
meditation okay so that would be a good
one to do during the tree because you're
offering good meditation to other people
okay first one is the grace if you have
food problems like me like you can't
stop eating cakes or okay if you have
food problems do number four the guide
you miss grace okay nice if you can't
stop yourself from eating or you eat too
much or you eat bad things you know ask
for help
this grace number four says I don't want
to eat to be beautiful or I don't want
to eat to be strong and someone asked me
a good question which I will repeat they
said get an eye on your sin you taught
many times the best teacher is someone
who is a good example you see like the
best way to teach is to follow what you
say if you're obviously following what
you say people will respect you and
listen to what you teach okay so they
said I like to eat carefully so my body
looks beautiful so people who are just
starting Buddhism will be attracted to
me and that's a good motivation okay
that's okay I bought a suit I bought a
Bulgarian Mafia suit because it looks
cool you know somebody told me military
younger days I said yeah that's what I'm
trying to do you know and the point
issues you know I always wanted you know
if any actually a Bulgarian lucky that
bar for me so you know that's okay
that's not pride that's I want to look
nice because I want more people to come
to class and so that's okay
that kind of motivation is not what
we're talking about here you know this
is a bad motivation you know I want to
look beautiful so I get more attention
or until my boyfriend likes me more it's
something like that okay more boys like
me okay number five and the sister Grace
is if you want to come back with some
cobbler which means if you want to
understand what the Buddha said okay if
you want to understand what the Buddha
said there's nothing better than some
cup
nothing ever never okay
all right and the last grace is very
very beautiful very very powerful grace
to Tampa angel okay bud you give me to
God you jumbo so that's that's a
beautiful one and in that one it's nice
to do a retreat you pretend you are her
you eat the food you offer the food to
her directly okay like this okay ready
I'm going to do number six I'm glad you
agree me I'm going to offer this to you
thanks okay got it
it's very cool it's a little
schizophrenia okay I'm gonna and I'm
offering to do that okay and it's very
powerful it's a very good custom okay
all right what happens that's good
enough to drink cappuccinos no they
don't need food they don't need water
they're not living on food or water okay
they don't need to drink it what happens
to a Buddha when they drink cappuccino
they don't get nervous they don't get
alert tasty emptiness again but didn't I
see Angeles before they had the company
more yes they saw emptiness here here
here but when we offer food to Buddha
we're supposed to imagine when it touch
their lips they get more emptiness like
and they feel super cool you know like
super cappuccino emptyness cappuccino
[Music]
wow that's good and you're and they
think I'm this year's team is even
deeper okay got it
and and it makes them super happy so we
call emptiness and bliss okay may I'm
empty mission bliss
okay got it so that's number six that's
going to embassy you have time during a
retreat to take your time to do your
graces so do it and learn them okay pick
one that's you want meditation you want
my genie what do you want you choose it
okay and and memorize it good to know it
okay if you say it for ten days it'll
come automatically you will start to
learn it okay and that's that's
wonderful to have that in your Dharma
toolkit okay all right we got about 20
more minutes one more number 24
meditation number 24 the ninth message
about the ninth refuge commitment is to
encourage other people to take Russians
okay the ninth refuge valve is to
encourage other people to take refuge
and I just want to talk about that I was
in Singapore Singapore has probably the
best follow-up programs in the world of
all the Dharma of Jenny Wong's group
because of Jenny Wong
they probably have the best follow-up
every almost a couple of times a week
you can do follow-ups and
with somebody or or you can go visit a
nursing home or you if they did it's
very regular and it's very organized
like Singapore people are so organized
to me not like anybody else in the world
so then I said so Denny what do you guys
doing you know this week and she said
we're having a sharing you know and I
kind of didn't know what she's talking
about I said well what's a sharing and
she says you know we get up and we share
as to what was shared
she's only shared DCI you know we we
shared this yeah I said all you're
teaching people she said no to look at
the like this is no we share we don't
teach gonna write oh that's cool
you know get your Michael teach it
Singapore people share and it feels much
better right it feels it moves you get
to say something also and I'm I don't
get up and say I'm the best person in
this room I know everything I also know
Tibetan grandmother's you know we don't
and so I will teach you you know and but
if you go to Singapore they will say I
will share with you my experience you
share with me your experience and and
let's help each other
you see it's mutual kind of thing so
this refuge valve by the way what's the
picture this lady is telling not sharing
okay and her friend is irritated stop
teaching me you know okay stop telling
me by the way this is very common
when people go home after a retreat at
Diamond Mountain and they tell their
family through the truth no please and I
can say anything will go wrong you know
microcell only I understand in this
whole family only I understand you know
and will quickly become the most
unpopular person in your family okay
so when your family there's a family
gathering and people see you they will
they will go the other way I hope she
doesn't tell me what to do okay so I
think with this message bell number nine
okay encouraged means people warning if
people are interested can share if
they're not interested don't bother them
okay one of the most
imitating things in the world is a new
Buddhist you know if you want to
alienate other people if you don't want
them to learn anything do like that
missionary become missionary right you
must believe what I believe and people
don't like it
okay nobody likes it I don't like it
someone starts talking to me like that
there are some groups in America they
come to your house they bang on your
door and and they go to the door and
they say do you believe in I believe in
what there's only one more dead
then you can't get them to get that foot
in your house it's like the camel and
and you can't get them out when I was in
the temple in New Jersey they used to
come and I told Rivage I said these
people keep coming back he said to bait
them just a bit down we have fun and
they were pretty nice anyway don't
irritate other people with your Buddhism
okay you can talk about you know
selfless but be careful they might put
you in the mental hospital okay don't
don't go crazy share with the people who
want to know but don't bother people
okay so we will do meditation number 24
we can think about how to share sweetly
like Singapore people and you can think
about right do i / - I'd tell people you
know do I share do I tell okay okay do I
have this bad habit of pushing my
religion on other people okay okay and I
think that's important for the refuge
Val okay all right I'm going to do a
little bit of the book just because I
like it mmm oh I thought it was in lemon
okay then let's take one question
okay that's a good question if I decide
to he asked each refuge commitment there
are 12 men each one should involve
vessels you know so if I let's say I'm
in general group they're very organized
they have assistant sharing leaders they
have sharing leaders they have what do
you call that in turn sharing leaders
it's very cool they have a very cool
system so how is that taking refuge if I
decide to share rather than tell what do
you think
yeah more protection for more people
more protection for more people I think
that the word message is a little weird
in English it's like refugee years
I think shelter or protection
I think protections pretty cool I'm not
comfortable with any of them I they all
they all have good points those three
words refuge shelter and protection but
I think sometimes think of it as
protection you know like we're going to
learn that in the debate class the
definition of taking refuge is in the
debate class today okay and they involve
protection